Okay so we have resumed on נ"ג Nun Gimel on the bottom
of נ"ד עמוד א' Nun Dalet Amud Aleph or where we are
looking at the משנה Mishnah about ברכות Brachot for a נס Nes
and we just spoke about the fact that you make a נס
Nes for a place that happened to רבים Rabbim and an individual
to whom it directly happens would make a ברכה Bracha for נס
Nes in a place where it happened to himself. And now we
pick up where with תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, it's about ten lines
from the bottom beginning of the line.
תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הרואה מעברות הים ומעברות הירדן ומעברות נחלי ארנון,
Haroeh ma'avarot hayam uma'avarot hayarden uma'avarot nachlei Arnon, so if you see
the sort of the fords the passing place in of the Red
Sea or of the Jordan River or of נחלי ארנון, Nachlei Arnon,
all these are places where miracles occurred. The גמרא Gemara will discuss
each one of these. אבני אלגביש, Avnei Elgavish, stones hailstones of אלגביש
Elgavish במורד בית חורון Bemorad Beit Choron in the place of you
know the descending the descent of בית חורון, Beit Choron, ואבן שביקש
לזרוק עוג מלך הבשן על ישראל. Ve'even shebikesh lizrok Og Melech HaBashan
al Yisrael.
Here's the first one that does not have a reference in the
תורה: Torah: the stone that עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech HaBashan wanted
to throw on the Jewish people. ואבן שישב עליה משה בשעה שעשה
יהושע מלחמה בעמלק,
Ve'even sheyashav aleha Moshe besha'ah she'asah Yehoshua
milchama be'Amalek, the stone that משה Moshe sat when he did a
war against when יהושע Yehoshua fought against עמלק, Amalek, which is interesting
because you know you might have thought that the location of the
war would have been the place of the נס. Nes. Here it's
focusing on the place where משה Moshe sat. ואשתו של לוט, Ve'ishto
shel Lot, if one sees לוט's Lot wife, the pillar of salt.
וחומת יריחו שנבלעה במקומה, Vechomat Yericho shenivle'ah bimkomah, the wall in יריחו
Yericho that was swallowed up in its location. על כולן צריך שיתן
הודאה ושבח לפני המקום. Al kulan tsarich sheyiten hoda'ah veshevach lifnei HaMakom.
On all of these
places or or you know or sites you have to give praise
to God. It's interesting that it does not mention a particular נוסח
הברכה Nusach HaBracha like our משנה, Mishnah,
and it might be obviously referring to that and it's also interesting
that it's not as focused on place you know as our משנה
Mishnah was. I mean it starts with place but then it moves
on to the stones of אלגביש Elgavish and so on you know
the pillar of salt of לוט Lot etc. Anyway let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. בשלמא מעברות הים, Bishlama ma'avarot hayam, I understand
the place where they passed over in the Red Sea דכתיב ויבאו
בני ישראל בתוך הים ביבשה. Dechtiv vayavo'u Bnei Yisrael betoch hayam bayabasha.
Okay so that was a miracle, the crossing of the Red Sea.
מעברות הירדן, Ma'avarot hayarden, the crossing of the ירדן, Yarden, the place
where they crossed. I don't know how we're supposed to know exactly
what this where this place is but anyway דכתיב, Dechtiv,
that we know that they crossed the ירדן Yarden river was a
there
in the time of יהושע. Yehoshua. I think it split because it
was a river the פסוקים Psukim say that a wall was created
at one point of the water and then the rest of the
water just emptied out. So it wasn't exactly the same but still
obviously was a miracle of the crossing of the ירדן. Yarden. דכתיב
ויעמדו הכהנים נשאי ארון ברית ה' בחרבה בתוך הירדן הכן, Dechtiv vaya'amdu
hakohanim nosei aron berit Hashem becharava betoch hayarden hachen, so the כהנים
Kohanim stood in the middle of the ירדן Yarden established fixed וכל
ישראל עברים בחרבה Vechol Yisrael overim becharava and and Israel was passing
through in the dry land עד אשר תמו כל הגוי לעבר את
הירדן Ad asher tamu kol hagoy la'avor et hayarden until the whole
nation passed through the ירדן. Yarden. So I understand both of those
are places of miracles. אלא מעברות נחלי ארנון מנלן, Ella ma'avarot nachlei
Arnon minalan, how do I know what is this thing about the
flat place ways passage way through the wadis of ארנון? Arnon? What
is that about? So דכתיב, Dechtiv, the verse says על כן יאמר
בספר מלחמת ה' את והב בסופה ואת הנחלים ארנון. Al ken ye'amar
besefer milchamot Hashem et vahev besufa ve'et hanechalim Arnon.
So this is obviously a שירה Shira in במדבר Bamidbar and it
says the you know it'll say in the book of the wars
of God את והב בסופה Et vahev besufa and the wadis נחלים
Nechalim of ארנון. Arnon.
So what does that mean? תנא את והב בסופה, Tana et vahev
besufa, what does this mean? שני מצורעים היו דהוו מהלכין בסוף מחנה
ישראל. Shnei mitsora'im hayu dehavu mehalechin besof machaneh Yisrael. So it's reading
בסוף Besof the בסופה, Besufa, that there were two מצורעים Mitsora'im that
were outside of the camp because a מצורע Mitsora is sent outside
of the camp and they were going outside מחנה ישראל, Machaneh Yisrael,
they were at the back of the camp. כי הוו קחליפי ישראל,
Ki havu kachalfei Yisrael,
when the Jewish people were passing by through and this is you
know as they were going they were right before they were about
to enter the land of Israel אתו אמוראי, Atsu Emora'ei, so the
אמוריים Emori'im came ועבדו להון נקירותא, Ve'avdu lehun nekiruta,
they made for them crevices caves in the walls of the mountains
that surrounded this passageway top of נ"ד עמוד ב'. Nun Dalet Amud
Bet. אטשו בהו, Atshu behu, they hid in them. אמרי כי חלפי
ישראל הכא נקטלינהו, Amri ki chalfei Yisrael hacha nakitlinun, they said when
the Jewish people pass through this you know this passageway between the
mountains
we'll kill them we'll you know throw down arrows on them guerrilla
warfare we'll attack them from above from our hiding places in the
caves in the mountain. ולא הוו ידעי דארון הוה מסגי קמייהו דישראל
Velo havi yadu de-aron havi masgi kameyhu de-Yisrael
they were not aware that the ארון Aron would pass in front
of the Israelite camp, והוה ממיך להו Vahava mamich lehu
and would level the mountains that were in front of them. וכיוון
דאתו ארון Kivan de-atsu Aron once the ארון Aron passed in front,
אזקו טורי בהדי הדדי Azku turei bahadi hadadi
the mountains sort of pressed one another. You have to imagine that
the idea is is that there were mountains, two mountains you know
on each side of this pathway and they were in opposite caves
of the mountains and and then the mountains sort of moved towards
one another and whatever protrusions from each one sort of entered into
the caves of the other and it killed all of them that
were hiding in the caves. I don't know what that has to
do with the ארון Aron leveling off the mountains because this wasn't
leveling the mountains. Maybe the point is it was leveling the road
by moving the mountains. But anyway so all the Amorites got killed
because the mountains moved.
וקטלינון Vakatlinun it killed all of them. מנחלי שמאי לנחלי ארנון Minachal
Shamai le-Nachle Arnon and then the blood flowed into the Wadi of
Arnon. כי אתו Ki atsu when they came ו-והב ve-Vahev when they
came to this place והב Vahev which is apparently a place, חזו
דמא דקנפיק מביני טורי hazu dama deka nafik mi-beyni turei they saw
the blood was coming from between the mountains. אתו ואמרו לישראל Atsu
ve-amru le-Yisrael so this is the מצורעים Metzora'im they were traveling behind
so presumably they saw the aftermath which the Israelites did not see,
you know the Israelites did not see, and they saw the blood
flowing down from the mountains and going into the Wadi of Arnon
all the way to this place called והב. Vahev. So they came
and they told Israel they told you know they told their fellow
Israelites ואמרו שירה ve-amru shira and they gave song.
So that's what it says, והב בסופה Vahev be-Sufa this place of
והב Vahev which was seen by the people going at the back
of the camp, את הנחלים ארנון et hanachalim Arnon and they saw
this miracle in the wadis of Arnon. והיינו דכתיב Vahainu dich'tiv that's
what's meant by the verse, ואשד הנחלים אשר נטה לשבת ער ונשען
לגבול מואב. Ve-eshed hanachalim asher nata leshevet Ar ve-nish'an ligvul Moav. So
אשד Eshed means the pouring of the wadi which is leaning towards
those who live in
ער Ar and because ער Ar was the name of the land
of מואב Moav was ער. Ar. So the mountain moved over, it
inclined towards ער Ar ונשען לגבול מואב ve-nish'an ligvul Moav you know
and also inclining towards the boundary of מואב. Moav. The idea is
the mountains inclined towards one another and this blood flew out. So
that is the ברכה bracha you say when you pass this wadi.
All right, so now we are clearly moving from places that are
what do you call it that are in the פסוקים pesukim to
more מדרשים midrashim although this is a מדרש Midrash that interprets the
פסוקים. pesukim. It is interesting especially when we get to the next
one which is not even based on a פסוק pasuk at all
about עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech ha-Bashan that you know it gets
to the question about מדרשים midrashim and whether חז"ל Chazal understood them
literally or were they there more for rhetorical purposes and so on.
If they're having you make a ברכה bracha it seems that at
least this they really believed actually occurred as a historical event. Okay
so that's one. Now we go
on, אבני אלגביש Avnei elgavish the hailstones of אלגביש Elgavish מאי mai
what is that? מאי אבני אלגביש? Mai avnei elgavish? תנא אבנים שעמדו
על גב איש וירדו על גב איש Tana avanim she-amdu al gav
ish ve-yardu al gav ish stones
that stood above one person and they fell down upon another person.
Two separate events. עמדו על גב איש זה משה Amdu al gav
ish zeh Moshe דכתיב והאיש משה ענו מאד dich'tiv ve-ha'ish Moshe anav
me'od
so they were suspended above משה. Moshe. So when was that that
hailstones were suspended above משה? Moshe? דכתיב ויחדלו הקולות והברד ומטר לא
נתך ארצה.
Dich'tiv va-yachdelu hakolot ve-habarad u-matar lo
nitach artzah. So the hail and the thunder ceased and it did
not descend to the ground. So the hailstones at the מכת ברד
makat barad after משה Moshe called on them to stop remained suspended
in mid-air. So that's על גב איש al gav ish it never
it was suspended above משה. Moshe. וירדו על גב איש Veyardu al
gav ish they descended זה יהושע zeh Yehoshua דכתיב קח לך את
יהושע בן נון איש אשר רוח בו. dich'tiv kach lecha et Yehoshua
bin Nun ish asher ruach bo. So יהושע Yehoshua is called an
איש. ish. דכתיב ויהי בנסם מפני בני ישראל
הם במורד בית חורון Dich'tiv va-yehi benosam mipnei Bnei Yisrael hem be-morad
Beit Choron so there you have מורד בית חורון morad Beit Choron
וה' השליך עליהם אבנים גדולות. va-Hashem hishlich aleihem avanim gedolot.
So this is when they were fighting against the you know against
the people living in כנען Kena'an and they there was a hail
storm when they were going in this place the descent of בית
חורון Beit Choron and if you and that is the אבני אלגביש.
avnei elgavish. So the place with משה Moshe is of course harder
to imagine when would you see those hailstones that suspended in mid-air,
but at least the second example presumably means if you're in this
place of בית חורון. Beit Choron. So it is talking at least
about a particular place.
Anyway, and we are
still linked to
פסוקים. psukim. Now we have this next one, אבן שבקש עוג מלך
הבשן לזרוק על ישראל. Even she-bikeish Og Melech ha-Bashan lizrok al Yisrael.
So the stone that עוג מלך הבשן Og Melech ha-Bashan wanted to
throw on ישראל. Yisrael. What is this? גמרא גמירי לה. Gemara gemiri
lah. So the גמרא Gemara tells you right out it's not a
פסוק, pasuk, this is a tradition.
אמר, Amar, עוג Og said to himself, let's see, how big is
the entire מחנה ישראל? Machaneh Yisrael? מחנה ישראל כמה הוי? Machaneh Yisrael
kama havei? Plus a פרסה. parsa. תלתא פרסי. Tlata parsei. Three pars-
pars- anyway, three of these parsangs.
A פרסה parsa is a- four מיל. mil. So it's about a
מיל. mil. A מיל mil is about a kilometer. So- so- so
three pars- pars- anyway, three of these parsangs
are about twelve kilometers. Anyway, איזיל ואיעקר טורא בר תלתא פרסי. Izil
ve-eikar tura bar tlata parsei. So that's how big the camp is.
איזיל ואיעקר טורא בר תלתא פרסי, Izil ve-eikar tura bar tlata parsei,
so he lifted up a mountain that was this big, it was
the entire width of the area of the Israelite encampment. ואישדי
עלייהו Ve-ishdi aleihu and though he said, I'm sorry, let me lift
up a mountain that's this big, ואישדי עלייהו ve-ishdi aleihu I'll throw
it on them, וקטלינו ve-katleinu and I'll wipe them all out with
throwing on them this one huge mountain. אזל, Azal, he went, so
it's no longer by the way a stone, now it's an entire
mountain that's, you know, twelve kilometers wide, which is what, like about
five miles or eight miles or something. Anyway,
אזל עקר טורא בר תלתא פרסי, Azal akar tura bar tlata parsei,
he lifted up a mountain that was this big, ואייתי על רישיה,
ve-aytei al reishei, he lifted it up over his head. ואייתי קודשא
בריך הוא. Ve-aytei Kudsha Brich Hu. So קודשא בריך הוא Kudsha Brich
Hu came, עליה קמצי, aleih kamtzei,
and he had like grasshoppers or ants come and start, you know,
chopping away at the- eating away at the mountain.
They must have been very quick workers. ונקבוהו, Ve-nakvuhu, they made holes
in the mountain, ונחת בצוואריה. ve-nachat be-tzavarei. So- so the mountain sort
of split as he was holding it over his head and it
sort of fell over his head. So- like it, you know, it
broke away from his hands and fell on top of his head.
הוה בעי למשלפה. Hava bei le-mishlafeh.
So he was trying to pull it out from- you know, it's
around his neck, like his neck is sticking out from through this
mountain, imagine. He tried to pull it out. משכי שיניה להאי גיסא
ולהאי גיסא. Mashchei shinei le-hai gisa u-le-hai gisa. His teeth extended- horizontally
in each direction and sort of hooked into the mountain, ולא מצי
למשלפה ve-lo matzi le-mishlafeh and he could not remove it. והיינו דכתיב.
Ve-hainu di-chtiv. And this is to fulfill the פסוק pasuk that says,
שיני רשעים שברת, Shinei rasha’im shibarta, You have broken the teeth of
the wicked. וכדרבי שמעון בן לקיש, U-che-de-Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, like רבי
שמעון בן לקיש Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish teaches. אמר רבי שמעון בן
לקיש, Amar Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish, מאי דכתיב שיני רשעים שברת? mai
di-chtiv shinei rasha’im shibarta? אל תקרי שברת, Al tikri shibarta, don't read
שברת, shibarta, אלא שרבבת, ela shirvavta, you extended. Okay,
so now we have עוג Og that's got this mountain over his
head and he's, you know, it's almost like this theater of the
absurd, you know, this mountain cracked over his head, his teeth are
in it, he's trying to yank it out and he can't. So
he's very vulnerable. And now what happens? משה Moshe is going to
come along and- and finish him off. So משה, Moshe, how- how
tall was משה? Moshe? עשר אמות. Eser amot. משה Moshe was עשר
אמות. eser amot. The גמרא Gemara learns this in another place because
it says משה Moshe spread the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, you know,
the- sort of- the roof- on top of the אהל מועד, Ohel
Moed, you know, that was made out of the tapestries. And the
אהל מועד Ohel Moed was עשר אמות eser amot tall. So משה,
Moshe, if he could spread the roof by himself, not on a
ladder, he was עשר אמות eser amot tall. So he was עשר
אמות. eser amot. שקיל נרגא בר עשר אמין. Shakil narga bar eser
amin. He took like a hatchet that was also עשר אמות eser
amot tall, שוור עשר אמין shavar eser amin he jumped up עשר
אמות. eser amot. So now he's- he's thirty אמות amot off of
the ground, which is, you know, like what, like about forty-five feet
or something like that.
Alright, so- he's forty-five feet off the ground, ומחייה בקרסוליה, u-machyei be-karsulei,
and by being forty-five feet he got up to the ankle of
עוג, Og, וקטליה ve-katlei and he killed him. Okay, so by hitting
him in the ankle, maybe it was a case of- who was
that, Achilles' heel, so this was the Ogian ankle. So somehow by
hitting him in the ankle, maybe it made him trip and then
he died because of the mountain, I don't know. Anyway, quite a
fantastical story, you know, but the interesting thing is that the גמרא
Gemara takes it- you know, some aspect of it literally if the
ברייתא Baraita is having making a ברכה. beracha. Now notice that the
ברייתא Baraita says the stone. The גמרא Gemara made it a much
more fantastical story than just as indicated by the ברייתא. Baraita. But
again, it's quite interesting, you know, the- you know, how much it
really took this literally. Maybe it also assumed that you know, there's
no stone to find, so it's more theoretical than actually practical. Anyway,
that's this מדרש Midrash about עוג. Og. והאבן שישב עליה משה. Ve-ha-even
she-yashav aleiha Moshe. How about the stone משה Moshe sat on?
Again we are still linked more with... I don't know why we're
focusing on the stone rather than on the what-do-you-call-it on the on
the place.
Okay, so now it continues: ואשתו של לוט, ve-ishto shel Lot, and
the wife of Lot. שנאמר, shene'emar, as it is said, ותבט אשתו
מאחריו, va-tabet ishto me-acharav, so his wife looked behind her, ותהי נציב
מלח, va-tehi netziv melach, and she became a pillar of salt. וחומת
יריחו, ve-chomat Yericho, the wall of Jericho, שנבלעה, she-nivla'ah, that was absorbed.
Now why does it say it was absorbed? We normally assume that
the wall of Jericho fell. What does it mean that the wall
of Jericho was absorbed? So דכתיב, de-chtiv, the verse says, ותפול החומה
תחתיה, va-tipol ha-choma tachtecha, the wall fell underneath itself. So it's understood
to mean how do you fall underneath yourself is that you get
absorbed into the ground, because it's underneath where the wall had been
standing. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask about this.
בשלמא כולו ניסא, bishlama kulu nisa, I understand all these were miracles,
אלא אשתו של לוט, ela ishto shel Lot, but the wife of
Lot, פורענותא היא, puranuta hu, that was a punishment. So even though
it was a punishment through miraculous means, but interestingly, and you could
have said maybe it's a punishment to a רשע, rasha, a wicked
person, interestingly the גמרא Gemara understands you would only make a ברכה
bracha on a miracle that had a that was like a salvation,
that brought about something good, not about punishment. So the גמרא Gemara
says, you know what, you're right.
דאמר ברוך דיין האמת. de-amar Baruch Dayan HaEmet. So you don't say,
you know, שעשה נס she-asa nes or שעשה ניסים. she-asa nisim. You
say ברוך דיין האמת, Baruch Dayan HaEmet, you make a different ברכה.
bracha. והא הודאה ושבח תניא, ve-ha hoda'ah ve-shevach tanya, but one minute,
it says you give thanks and praise to God. תני על לוט
ועל אשתו מברכים שתים. tani al Lot ve-al ishto mevarechin shtayim. No,
so here's how you have to change the text of the ברייתא.
Beraita. For Lot and his wife you give two ברכות. brachot. על
אשתו אומר ברוך דיין האמת ועל לוט אומר ברוך זוכר הצדיקים.
al ishto omer Baruch Dayan
HaEmet ve-al Lot omer Baruch Zocher HaTzadikim.
Okay, because for Lot it was good he was remembered. Now actually
אברהם Avraham was the צדיק tzadik that was remembered. So again, this
is quite fascinating, especially like I mentioned to you, I mentioned earlier
today that there's a debate of the ראשונים Rishonim whether this is
with שם ומלכות. shem u-malchut. If it's without שם ומלכות shem u-malchut
you can understand that, you know, we're very flexible, it's just words
of praise, it's not a formal נוסח הברכה. nusach ha-bracha. But assuming
it is a formal נוסח הברכה, nusach ha-bracha, you know, again, that
we keep on coming up with new versions, so we're not just
saying שעשה נס, she-asa nes, we're saying, you know, we're saying ברוך
זוכר הצדיקים. Baruch Zocher HaTzadikim.
Also, this is not a נס, nes, you know, that occurred לאבותינו.
le-avoteinu. It's not a נס nes that occurred to us nationally. This
is the first one that was very local, I mean it was
a relative of אברהם, Avraham, but it wasn't to us as a
nation, and we're making it, and we're making it much after the
fact. So it is interesting that the גמרא Gemara then modifies if
it's all, it creates this ברכה. bracha. It's also interesting that this
idea ברוך דיין האמת Baruch Dayan HaEmet is even when it's not
some new event, but just seeing something that evokes that feeling of
דיין האמת. Dayan HaEmet. Now we have that, for example, a ברכה
bracha a person makes when he visits a cemetery. So it's, you
know, even if it's not a recent death, but experiencing these types
of sights that evoke that sense of God is דיין האמת. Dayan
HaEmet. But we should note that it's different than what we've been
saying now because it is not an immediate experience and it's not
a national historical experience, and nevertheless we have these ברכות. brachot.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi
Yochanan, אפילו בשעת כעסו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, afilo bi-sh'at ka'aso shel
HaKadosh Baruch Hu, even when God is angry, זוכר הצדיקים, zocher ha-tzadikim,
He remembers the righteous. שנאמר ויהי בשחת אלוהים את ערי הככר ויזכור
אלוהים את אברהם, shene'emar va-yehi be-shachet Elohim et arei ha-kikar va-yizkor Elohim
et Avraham, when He was wiping out the cities of the valley
He remembered אברהם. Avraham. וישלח את לוט מתוך ההפכה, va-yeshalach et Lot
mi-toch ha-hafecha, and He saved Lot. So, you know, it doesn't sound
like such a shock to us, I mean obviously you would expect
God to be protecting the righteous and so on. I mean here
maybe the חידוש chiddush is that Lot wasn't righteous. He protected Lot
for the sake of אברהם, Avraham, and maybe Lot was deserving to
be wiped out. It also is probably in conversation with other מדרשים
midrashim that say that at the time when, you know, God gives
like the forces of destruction or the angel of destruction the right
to destroy, אינו מבחין בין צדיק לרשע. eino mavchin bein tzadik le-rasha.
Like, why, you know, he doesn't distinguish between righteous and wicked, like
why people had to stay in their homes on the night of
פסח, Pesach, ולא יתן המשחית לבוא בתיכם לנגוף. ve-lo yiten ha-mashchit lavo
el bateichem linigof. So there is other sort of approaches that at
times of destruction, it's not always just. So here it's saying no,
God does remember the righteous and even Lot who was the nephew
of אברהם. Avraham. Okay, now continuing on this list, וחומת יריחו שנבלעה,
ve-chomat Yericho she-nivla'ah, the wall of Jericho that was absorbed. So the
גמרא Gemara says, the wall of Jericho was absorbed in its place?
והא נפלה, ve-ha nafla, it fell down. שנאמר ויהי כשמוע העם את
קול השופר ויריעו העם תרועה גדולה, shene'emar va-yehi kishmoa ha-am et kol
ha-shofar va-yariu ha-am teruah gedolah, they made a big shofar blast, ותפול
החומה תחתיה, va-tipol ha-choma tachtecha, the wall fell under, you know, underneath.
So it says fell. So now I said part of the דרשה
drasha might be the word תחתיה. tachtecha. How do you fall underneath
yourself is that you get absorbed into the ground? absorbed, but here's
the גמרא'ס Gemara's explanation: כיוון דפותיה ורומה כי הדדי נינהו. Keivan defotya
veruma ki hadadi ninhu. The גמרא Gemara says, doesn't tell us how
it knows this, that its width and its height was the same,
was as wide as it was high. So therefore if it just
fell down, it would still be the same wall. Maybe it would
have moved 20 feet, but it would still have the same height
because now what had been the width would now become the height.
So therefore since that was the case, משום הכי אכלועי איבלוע, mishum
hachi achloei ivloa, therefore it had to be swallowed in order for
it to really fall down. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב. Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav. Okay, so that was a whole discussion about these
historical miracles of the past. Again, a little interesting to note a
shift a little bit from not all about place, some about objects,
some about you know the approach to the various מדרשים midrashim and
so on. Now however we move to another point which is very
relevant להלכה, le-halacha, which is about without something that's obviously miraculous, but
a general obligation to make a ברכה bracha of thanksgiving when one
comes out of a dangerous situation and in particular four in particular.
So let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Rav, ארבעה צריכים להודות, arbaah tzrichim lehodot, four have to
give thanks to God. יורדי הים, yordei hayam, those that go down
to the ocean, הולכי מדברות, holchei midbarot, those that go in the
desert, ומי שהיה חולה ונתרפא, umi shehayah choleh venitrapa, somebody was sick,
obviously with a serious illness, and got better, ומי שהיה חבוש בבית
האסורים ויצא, umi shehayah chavush beveit haasurim veyatza, and somebody that was
bound up in a jail and came out. יורדי הים מנלן? דכתיב,
yordei hayam minalan dechtiv, and now all of this is a דרשה
drasha on this one פרק perek of תהילים, Tehillim, which is all
about giving thanks to God and it's פרק קז Perek Kuf Zayin
and that פרק perek I believe begins, here let me get out
the
תנ״ך. Tanach. פרק קז Perek Kuf Zayin begins the following way.
It says הודו להשם כי טוב כי לעולם חסדו. Hodu laHashem ki
tov ki leolam chasdo. Right? Starts with the הודו להשם Hodu laHashem
and then goes on about the different people that give thanks to
God. So the גמרא Gemara also you know speaks about that these
are the events on the basis of which one brings a קרבן
תודה, Korban Todah, a קרבן Korban of thanksgiving mentioned in the תורה,
Torah, but the תורה Torah does not mention the particular circumstances that
lead to it. So four have to give thanks. Let's take a
look. יורדי הים מנלן yordei hayam minalan? דכתיב, Dechtiv, now just quoting
from the פסוקים. psukim. יורדי הים באוניות, Yordei hayam baoniyot, those that
go into the ocean with boats, המה ראו מעשי השם, hemah rau
maasei Hashem, they saw the miracles of God, ואומר ויעמד
רוח סערה ויעלו שמים ירדו תהומות, veomer vayaamed ruach searah vayalu shamayim
yardu tehomot, he saw a tremendous you know wind and the waves
went up to the heaven and they went into the they went
to the depths. ואומר יחוגו וינועו כשיכור, veomer yachogu veyanuu kashikor, they
swayed like a drunkard, ואומר, veomer, right you know when the waves
were beating against the boat and if there were storms, ויצעקו אל
השם בצר להם וממצוקותיהם יוציאם, vayitzaku el Hashem batzar lahem umimetzukoteihem yotziem,
they called out to God when it was when they were in
anguish, וממצוקותיהם יוציאם, umimetzukoteihem yotziem, God took them out from their from
their despair or from you know from their anguish. ואומר יקם סערה
לדממה, veomer yakem searah lidmamah, God made the storm become silent, ואומר
וישמחו כי ישתוקו, veomer vayishmechu ki yishtoku, they were they rejoiced when
the storm had silenced, ואומר יודו להשם חסדו ונפלאותיו לבני אדם, veomer
yodu laHashem chasdo veniflaotav livnei adam, praise God for God's kindness, ונפלאותיו
לבני אדם, veniflaotav livnei adam, God's wonders, speak of God's wonders to
people. Okay, so that's one פסוקים psukim about those that go to
the ocean, really just quoting פסוקים, psukim, it's really just pointing out
what's in this פרק perek of תהילים. Tehillim. הולכי מדברות, Holchei midbarot,
those that go in the wilderness or in the in the desert,
מנלן דכתיב תעו במדבר בישימון דרך עיר מושב לא מצאו, minalan dechtiv
tau bamidbar bishimon derech ir moshav lo matzau, they wandered in the
desert in the desolate places, עיר מושב לא מצאו, ir moshav lo
matzau, there was no settled city. ויצעקו אל השם, Vayitzaku el Hashem,
they cried out again to God, וידריכם בדרך ישרה, vaydrichem bederech yesharah,
and God had them led them to walk in the straightaway in
the straight path, יודו להשם חסדו, yodu laHashem chasdo, they will thank
God for God's kindness. מי שחלה ונתרפא, mi shechalah venitrapa, somebody that
got sick and got healed,
דכתיב אוילים מדרך פשעם ומעוונותיהם יתענו. dechtiv evilim miderech pisham umeavonoteihem yitanu.
This is interesting because here it assumes as opposed to the other
cases, here it assumes that this is a result of sin. The
פסוקים, psukim, and it says those that are foolish due to their
sins, ומעוונותיהם יתענו, umeavonoteihem yitanu, and they are afflicted because of their
of their iniquity. כל אוכל תתעב נפשם, Kol ochel titaev nafsham, so
when you are sick you don't want to eat any food, it's
disgusting, ויזעקו אל השם בצר להם, vayizaku el Hashem batzar lahem, they
called out to God, וישלח דברו וירפאם, vayishlach devaro ve-yirpaem, God sent
his word and healed them. יודו להשם חסדו, Yodu laHashem chasdo, they
will thank God for God's kindness. So that's number three. מי שהיה
חבוש בבית האסורים, Mi shehayah chavush beveit haasurim, somebody that was imprisoned
and was freed, מנלן דכתיב יושבי חושך וצלמות, minalan dechtiv yoshei choshech
vetzalmavet, those that dwell in the in the darkness, כי המרו אמרי
אל, ki himru imrei el, again assumed that it was a result
of sin because they rebelled against the word of God, ואומר ויכנע
בעמל לבם, veomer vayachna beamal libam, God caused their hearts to be
humbled through their through their affliction, ואומר ויזעקו אל השם בצר להם.
veomer vayizaku el Hashem batzar lahem. You're noticing a theme here, a
theme. here they called out to God when they were in anguish.
ואומר יוציאם מחשך וצלמות, v'omer yotzi'em me-choshech ve-tzal-mavet, God took them out
of the darkness. ואומר יודו להשם חסדו. v'omer yodu l'Hashem chasdo. Okay,
so that was a lot of quoting of the פסוקים, psukim, but
anyway these are the four people that once they get out of
their difficult positions, the פסוקים psukim say that they shall say praise
God. So מאי מברך? mai mevarech? So now the גמרא Gemara assumes
that it's not just a generic obligation to pray, but that there
is some type of a specific text that they should be saying.
So what do they say? So אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda,
ברוך גומל חסדים טובים. Baruch gomel chasadim tovim. So now this should
be a text that you're familiar with, right? Blessed is God who
rewards us with good kindness or who compensates us, pays us back
with God's good kindness. אביי אומר, Abaye omer, so I mean obviously
our נוסח nusach is a little different, ברוך אתה השם הגומל לחייבים
טובות שגמלני כל טוב. Baruch Atah Hashem hagomel l'chayavim tovot she-gemalani kol
tov. But anyway גומל חסדים טובים. gomel chasadim tovim. אביי אמר, Abaye
amar, וצריך לאודויי קמי עשרה, ve-tzarich l'oduyei kammai asara, you have to
do it in front of ten, דכתיב וירוממוהו בקהל עם, de-chtiv ve-yeromemuhu
bi-kehal am, quoting the פסוקים psukim again, they will praise God, they
will elevate God in a congregation of people. So a קהל kahal
is ten. מר זוטרא אמר, Mar Zutra amar, ותרי מינייהו רבנן, ve-trei
mineihu rabanan, two out of those ten have to be rabbis or
sages, שנאמר ובמושב זקנים יהללוהו, she-ne'emar u-ve-moshav zekenim yehaleluhu, the verse says,
and in the
presence of elders they will praise God. So elders is two, so
there has to be two sages. So מתיב רב אשי, metiv Rav
Ashi, ואימא כולהו רבנן, ve-eima kulehu rabanan, maybe they should all be
rabbis or sages? So says no, מי כתיב בקהל זקנים? mi ktiv
bi-kehal zekenim? No, it doesn't say congregation of elders. בקהל עם כתיב,
bi-kehal am ktiv, a congregation of the people, and then it says
in the presence of elders. ואימא בי עשרה ותרי רבנן, ve-eima bei
asara ve-trei rabanan, maybe we should need both, meaning how what makes
you think that the two is part of the ten? Maybe ten
of the normal
people plus two sages? How do you know the two are part
of the ten? The גמרא Gemara says קשיא. kashya. All right, that's
a problem. We don't exactly know. Obviously nowadays anyway we're not מדקדק
medakdek on the two sages part, we're just מדקדק medakdek on the
עשרה asara and the מנין. minyan. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says
a story about this. רב יהודה חלש, Rav Yehuda chalash, רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda got sick. ואתפח, ve-itpach, he got better. על לגביה רב
חנא בגדתאה, al legabei Rav Chana Bagdata'ah, רב חנא בגדתאה Rav Chana
Bagdata'ah came to him, ורבנן, ve-rabanan, and the rabbis, meaning the students,
ואמרי ליה, ve-amrei leh, so they said to him, בריך רחמנא דיהבך
ניהלן, brich rachmana di-yavach n'halan, blessed is God that He has given
you to us, meaning saved you, given you back to us, ולא
יהבך לעפרא, ve-lo yavach l'afra, and hasn't given you to the dust.
That's a nice little line. אמר להו, amar lehu, so he said
to them,
פטרתון יתי מלאודויי, patartun yati me-l'oduyei, you've exempted me from giving thanks.
You gave thanks for me, I don't have to do it myself.
So והאמר אביי בעי אודויי באפי עשרה, ve-ha amar Abaye ba'ei oduyei
be-appei asara, wait a minute, what about the fact that you need
a מנין? minyan? So the גמרא Gemara says דהוו בי עשרה, de-havu
bei asara, okay, there was a מנין minyan there, there were ten
people there, said he came with all the rabbinic students. So the
גמרא Gemara says והא איהו לא קא מודה, ve-ha ihu lo ka
modeh, but you have to be the one to give thanks, here's
somebody else's thanking. The גמרא Gemara says לא צריך דעני בתרייהו אמן.
lo tzarich de-ani batraihu amen. He said אמן. Amen. So here you
have a very interesting thing, right, because of the idea of saying
אמן. Amen. We've been discussing until now things that are very personal
to you, תפילה, tefillah, ברכות הנהנין, birchot ha-nehenin, ברכת המזון, birchat ha-mazon,
about does it really work to be שומע כעונה shome'a k'oneh or
not. Here obviously you're the one that needs to give thanks and
we see the power of אמן Amen that at least it counts
equivalent as if you had given thanks, which is very interesting in
that larger context. It's also interesting, whatever happened to the fact that
it didn't have שם ומלכות, shem u-malchut, right? It didn't have ברוך
אתה השם, Baruch Atah Hashem, if they חז"ל Chazal created actually a
formal ברכה. bracha. So תוספות Tosafot says no, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda
was a student of רב, Rav, and רב Rav says you don't
need שם ומלכות shem u-malchut for a ברכה. bracha.
So that's interesting, right, because again but it does raise that question,
how much has this crystallized into a formal ברכה bracha text or
how much is it more sort of like guidelines of giving thanks
and we're not really dealing with a very defined ברכה bracha text.
I should mention also that this גמרא Gemara evokes a very similar
גמרא Gemara by
ליל סדר Leil Seder where the story is that one of the
אמוראים Amoraim said to a slave, what would you do if your
master would free you? And he says oh I would thank him
and praise him and so on and so forth. He said oh
you exempted us from saying מה נשתנה. Ma Nishtana. So that somehow
by somebody else sort of saying the relevant thing in your presence
it exempts you from having to do it. So this a little
bit this is an echo of that although obviously there are different
הלכתי halachic considerations. Let's just read one more line.
אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav Yehuda, since we had been quoting רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, another line of רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda, שלושה צריכים
שימור, shlosha tzrichim shimur, three people need protection in particular, apparently from
the מזיקין mazikin who are jealous or otherwise make these people are
vulnerable. ואלו הן, ve-elu hen, these are they: חולה, choleh, a sick
person who's vulnerable so the מזיקין mazikin want to get them, so
you should be around to protect him, maybe you're not exactly clear
how you protect, maybe just your presence. חולה, choleh, חתן... chatan... And
a חתן וכלה chatan vekallah and this is where we get the
idea of having שומרים shomrim for the חתן וכלה. chatan vekallah. I
know people have שומרים shomrim for the חתן, chatan, I didn't know
people, I don't know if people are so מקפיד makpid about it
for the כלה. kallah. Anyway, this is where it comes from. במתניתא
be-masnisa in the ברייתא braisa we taught. רש"י Rashi says it's cause
they're jealous of the שמחה simcha of the חתן וכלה. chatan vekallah.
In a ברייתא braisa we taught: חולה חיה חתן וכלה. choleh chaya
chatan vekallah. It adds also a woman who is giving, who has
just given birth, also because she is vulnerable cause she is sick.
ויש אומרים אף אבל, ve-yesh omrim af avel, even a mourner who
apparently because one bad thing happened maybe also is vulnerable. ויש אומרים
אף תלמידי חכמים בלילה, ve-yesh omrim af talmidei chachamim ba-lailah, even תלמידי
חכמים talmidei chachamim at night, not exactly clear what that is about,
but again, maybe some sense about being jealous or whatever, not exactly
clear. Okay, we will end with that and pick up at the
bottom of נד עמוד ב nun daled amud beis tomorrow. לילה טוב
layla tov to everyone.